right so hello Marilyn and thanks for
making time for us to have this
conversation I would love to start by
you telling a little bit about your
journey of how I know you now live at
Finland where I'm working with in Hong
College where we have a connection
because I used to work there before and
you moved there and and yeah
rather than me introducing you I'd love
for you to tell a little bit your story
how did you get interested in in the
whole integral framework and what made
you feel that cities is where you wanted
to give your focus to to the Integra
story okay thank you
Daniel and it's a wonderful way to begin
this year and this decade of 2020 with
you I have a interesting background
around the integral framework that sort
of grew naturally my career started with
developing individuals and then I
started working with leaders and teams
and organizations and sectors and then
communities and there was a point at
which I had the experience of being
invited to look at the city and I at
first I would call since I live in
pintor and an experience this experience
almost still a small boy saying this is
where your next step is and I thought
well I don't do cities my husband builds
them he was a building contractor no so
I thought about it for a long time I
realized my whole career was about
looking at and somehow catalyzing the
development of human systems so I said
okay I'll look at the city as a human
system that's a good idea
and I then began to realize that the
fractal patterns that I had discovered
in working at smaller scales of human
systems also we're all contained in the
city and the city itself as a human
system is a large
fractal pattern that at first I would
say it's the human system writ large and
it's not just about a single human but
it's about how do we live together so
the patterns in the city represent the
systems and relationships that we've
learned as humans enable us to live
together
of course over our histories we have
been more than successful and have
expanded and encroached in the context
in which we live in in our environments
which you're so much an expert about and
I realized that in order for cities to
be ah a fractal they must in some way
start to integrate reintegrate with
their ecology with their environments so
at about the time where I was looking at
this I had just graduated with going
back to school um and I did a doctorate
in learning and leadership and self
organizing communities it was an online
community I was working with Margaret
Wheatley's work and the Peconic
community of conversations and what that
helped me to do was to see exactly how I
could find the fractal patterns by
listening to language by listening to
conversation and waking up to
consciousness and culture as being very
important to being able to see the city
as a whole and when I discovered can
Wilbur's work in the integral model I
saw okay we've got consciousness and
culture that go with the technology and
the systems of the city with the
behaviors and the systems and together
these makes a very nice complimentary
for and so the for whatever calls that
the Tetra arising of these realities
helped me to be able to see the city as
first of all whole and then I was very
interested in retaining that it be a
living system and that it be
evolutionary so that I recognized the
city was very dynamic so
those were sort of my quote early
beginnings of looking at the city
through an integral lens and holding it
and respecting it as a living
evolutionary system yeah I mean there's
so much that I would love to pick up on
what you just said one of what you
called the fractal integration the guy
was one of the really begins insights
for me when I was studying like after
after being a true maja college doing
the Masters in holistic science and
during that time through contact with
people like David oh and John Todd and
Nancy Jack Todd realizing that the power
of design and particularly the role of
human intention in creating the world
and kind of made me realize that we we
really need to pay attention to the
upstream end of design and to some some
extent that's what I see you do with
this this integral approach to the city
to to bring in the bridge between how we
bring forth the system through how we
see the world and how then what we bring
forth also influences how we see the
world so this this this kind of feedback
loop between your design and worldview
that is so often ignored and then we
were surprised that we keep creating
systems that are actually degenerative
and not these self-propagating evolving
systems that fall into sync with the
larger nested nosov wholeness nature
life as a planetary process transforming
yeah oh yeah yeah totally because after
I went through this stage of discovering
I had something I could say about the
city then I was working in my small city
in British Columbia Abbotsford in Canada
and they asked me I was part of the
board of the Abbotsford Community
Foundation and they said well we we want
to sort of reexamine well how do we make
grants this year but what do we
really know about our city and I
realized after I finished doing my
doctoral work I had answered the
questions of how to understand
complexity and look at at community in
very different ways but I really didn't
know how to take the message home and
once they asked that question I said oh
I think I might be able to help you
answer that question what we know about
our city and then I started to create
new ways of finding the data that I
could express to them in graphic form
about the value systems in the city
about how the city was part of a context
how the city itself had multiple
intelligences and so when I finished
this work then the first books started
to emerge from me and in that first book
I really identified that the city had
multiple intelligences and as you say
the intelligences weren't just internal
but the first step I called it Kahn
texting intelligences and they were
intelligences for knowing the ecology of
a setting of the city they were about
emergence and knowing that we were on an
evolutionary path that they had also an
integral this this co-arising of
consciousness culture behaviors and
systems and that they were living so
many people forget there are generations
and cities and now it isn't just three
generations we can have - we might in
some places be pushing those seven
generations that are contained in the
city I also looked at the intelligences
of the individual inner and outer and
the collective the cultural and the
social and then a set of strategic
intelligences the first one I put there
was the one of inquiry now not knowing
how can we inquire together about what
it is that we want to know and just
briefly that that's really so at the
center of when I realized what is the
process that would create regenerative
cultures
that eye expressions off place in place
where you have that dynamic again where
we are one at the same time this is like
emergent properties of the system in our
place in our city in our buyer region
and at the same time were creative
agents in it that is is really like how
do we actively as regenerative cultures
create cultures that um that adapt to
place an express place as a like the
whole bio cultural uniqueness of where
you live but for me that that is at the
core of creating regenerative cultures
and yeah that just came up when you said
that and that's another place that we
would resonate because the inquiry these
intelligences I I went on afterwards and
so once we start to use inquiry then
we're starting to use a whole set of
systems to know one another better to
develop the relationships to listen to
one another and I did a lot of learning
in it um prototyping in Abbotsford and
then as people started to learn about my
work they invited me to come to their
places and I'll always I would start
with well let let us bring together what
I call the four voices of the city so
the four voices would sit in inquiry and
we would listen to what we know about
each other what's working around here
what's not working around here and what
do we imagine for the future so we would
call forth what people were holding in
their hearts but not necessarily sharing
with each other and by listening to each
other's stories people Woods who had
known each other for 20 years that I
never knew that about you and all of a
sudden there was a heart opening as well
as an opening of the intellect and we
started to see how we made the
particular culture that makes up our our
different cities how did you how did you
in this process how did you slow down
process enough that as you were asking
people to tell stories about that place
and what works what doesn't work I was
just thinking he could so easily spiral
into some kind of political discussion
or a conflict of opinions so there must
be a skillful way of saying no no we're
harvesting perspectives out of the
collective beehive that is our community
yeah Oh a really good example is the
city I worked with in Oklahoma in the
States
Durant so they asked me to come and work
with their community because some key
leaders had actually been doing
leadership development and
organizational development and then they
looked at each other and said what would
happen if we did this for the community
so when they asked me I said well I have
to come and and see if your community
has the energy for an inquiry and that's
what I look for I said would you please
convene for me the four voices of the
city the citizens the civic managers the
business innovators and the third sector
or the civil society so we had about
three or four people from each of those
voices and our first circle was just
those three questions what's working
around here what's not working what you
imagine for the future and describe a
story that that connects you emotionally
to the city out of that we realized
there was energy there was energy for
change energy for moving forward and
then we created they said to me okay
let's then give us a proposal for a
long-term change process and I gave him
a proposal for ten years but just not
normal to have a proposal for so long
but the first number of years really
were about convening series of dialogue
circles not only with the four voices
but around key themes so we brought
together themes around the economy and
education we brought together themes
around health and community we brought
together themes
around culture and well-being so all of
these three that there said there were
three sets of themes but each circle had
a different way of being assembled first
we brought together thought leaders then
we actually published what we discovered
and we published it in the community
newspaper and on the website then we
took it forward to the citizens and said
here's here's what our thought leaders
have said about it like what have you
got to say about it in small circles
where they gave their own authentic
feedback it wasn't just you know
parroting what they thought others had
said we we reassure that and then we
brought it to the policymakers and so we
said to the policy makers here's what
our thought leaders and our citizens
have said about education and the
economy what would prevent you from
helping us to actually implement these
ideas and the policy makers were usually
the ones that were the most surprised
because so many policy makers work in
very circumstances where they're
adversarial you know parliamentarians in
particular but also all kinds of
bureaucracies work in very adversarial
situations and they would be held safe
to express their own authentic views
when we found the this combination of
the thought leaders and the citizens and
the policy makers after publishing them
and then reconvening another set around
other themes over that that took us
three years this took us it wasn't
instant and when I told us in this case
is it you and the client in the city
like how did you get the engagement yeah
so so when I'm when remember I said the
invitation came from two leaders so they
were obviously expressing and
energy and I wanted to see where else
was the energy in the city and so did
they because they knew that they
couldn't carry it just on their own they
wanted the involvement of the rest of
their their citizens in the city and the
rest of the businesses and all of the
four voices and so we basically made
propulsive invitations to the thought
leaders and an open invitation to the
public and then go back to the propose
of invitations to the policy makers so
in that way we kept kind of breathing in
and breathing out but always finding the
energy for change and then they started
to notice it and it started to grow one
thing duranta that was very it turned
out to be an extremely good strategy was
they created something called imagine
Durant and had a board and the board
consisted of the three or four voices as
well and in the time that I was there at
the end of four years we had gone
through four go through three city
managers and three mayor's so if we had
depended only on being in City Hall I
doubt if the process had continued
because it originated outside City Hall
but it always invited them in and
included them but it was because we had
before voices and the momentum was built
naturally who find them because with
processes like I mean this is this is
wonderful to hear because it's like to
me it's it describes this living the
questions that is at the core of Rhian
habit in place in in a way that we we
might have a future but I in my
experience but often stops processes
like that from really getting going
is that something needs to resource the
initial catalysts the people who who are
even just having the idea we should
constantly bring everybody together how
like we're gonna call a meeting maybe we
should talk to Marilyn and bring her
wisdom into this story like somebody
needed to resource that and how was that
resource because that's more
doesn't spot yeah well the resourcing at
the beginning was interesting as I
mentioned it was the president of one of
the largest community banks in the city
and the chief of the Choctaw Nation they
had both been doing personal leadership
development they had both really done
the work and noticed their own change in
themselves and because of that they took
it to organizational development and
they both been working with an
organization you might have heard of in
Texas called Stegen out of Dallas who
who does all of this leadership and
organizational development work using an
integral frame and when they asked about
who does this work in community you
probably know Barrett Brown was one of
the faculty and he said oh well you
should check with Maryland Hamilton she
has she's actually you know started to
do that work so they called me up and
and asked me to come I was very
skeptical at the beginning because I was
well aware that doing the work at the
community and city level would be much
messier much less controllable than
either leadership or organizational
development because everybody's a
volunteer everybody but they chose to
bring in their their first board and
they started to resource it by asking
for the four voices all to contribute
time money and effort and that's that's
how we move forward but always around
energy it wasn't like thou shalt there
was no no it was looking for the
positive response and resonance and
building on that and amplifying it that
that's a lesson I learned from Margaret
Wheatley early on you know if you want
to improve the health of the system
connect it to more of itself find the
energy and amplify it so that's what I
always do is I go looking for the energy
and it doesn't have to come from City
Hall in this way it can come from the
citizens it could come from I could come
from business it could come from and in
this case there was a businessperson and
a cultural theater you know the whole
nation of the Choctaw Nation was was
really they were they were instrumental
in
being co-catalyst and what would you say
there because that that energy work that
of systemic energy work you're just
referring to particularly in this day
and age where where it seems to be a
tendency towards polarization and people
stop listening to each other because
they just create their little categories
and then the minute they hear a certain
meme they just put somebody into the
category and stop listening to that
person and so it's so easy for those
kind of public dialogues and inquiry
processes to do to have flashpoints
where people stop moving forward for the
sake of the whole for the care of
creating a healthier system and start
going into conflict how do you how do
you work that like how you how do you
guide energies so they stay generative
and regenerative rather than
degenerative and destructive oh that's a
good question and I think that part of
the answer would come from I never work
on my own so I called together a team
and in this case once I found that there
was energy and Durrant then I called
together the first team to come and help
me hold that very first sound dialogues
with with thought leaders and then we
looked to find local leaders so we were
wanting to always make sure what we were
doing was growing local capacity so the
capacity and we were able to do that and
they started to generate started to
become quite confident interestingly the
first executive director of the imagined
rent had never done any of this kind of
work and when we hired her she had been
doing smoking cessation smoking
cessation work for a bureaucracy but so
we knew she was working with health and
we knew she could work with some pretty
tough characters in the room because she
was in an area that smoking was still
very popular and but she'd never done
any of this her first year she was in
just sort of like almost fear and terror
could we carry this off could she just
would follow the design that we had for
this and by the end of the first year
she could do it all she could manage it
all she could call in the small group
facilitators and we started to find that
for the initial meetings that were I was
looking for as many local and American
especially um facilitators to
co-facilitate with me so it was evident
to people we were growing our own
capacities and I think that what
prevented us from polarizing was we were
always asking another question I learned
from Margaret Wheatley and that was who
else should be here who else should be
here because it isn't just us so we
would look for always pushing the
envelope of younger generations older
generations genders interests just as
much diversity as possible so we always
built diverse diversity into the
equation and if it didn't show up we
proposal II went after it this is
fascinating to me exactly just last week
I had a conversation with Bill Reid from
Regenesis group and so much what you
just described is really central to what
working in a place sourced regenerative
practice with the community is all about
- really like building capacity you
mentioned is really at the heart or even
in with Bill I had this conversation
that that the first place is personal
development which is both of oneself -
to learn how to collaborate how to
invite more people in how to hold these
processes but then to also the next
stage out is build the capacity of the
team to do this work together and and
and that's really where most of the
magic happens because then you create a
self-perpetuating like UBF
yeah yeah after them you you opposed an
idea impose an idea of this would be
healthier in the city so let's do this
but it's a much slower process much
slower and but it's an evolutionary
process that enables the system to heal
itself and to evolve it sounds for me
but I just listening to you is so
interesting to see how is a whole
community out there learning
regenerative practice yes but then
there's all this wealth in the community
you are very connected with the wider
integral community that that have also
done this kind of systemic work and I'm
just wondering how do we increase
learning to build bridges between these
communities in ways that that really
serve both of them and and serve the
world so that the higher purpose yeah so
now you're coming into sort of you know
flash-forward ten years I will just give
you a little completion around Durham
because ah so at the end of four years
we actually did the rest of those
intelligences which included putting
together a strategic mesh worked plan we
were navigating ten twenty thirty years
forward we knew what our purpose they
discovered their purpose they were able
to articulate their values and they knew
they had to evolve at their own speed
and that was something I told them all
along I said I could not predict for
them how fast this would be because it
would depend on how fast their uptake
was how fast they could share together
so at the end of four years though
because they had this and one of the
things they were uncharacteristically
good at I say uncharacteristically
because a lot of these systems are not
good strategic implementation they were
quite good at that and so they said ah
we think we can take this on now and and
we're going to go for it because we know
those sort of goals and who isn't going
to be involved in what we're going to
set for our first year or five year
tenure
intentions and they had it all mapped
out but with enough wiggle room that
they knew that they
could go with with the flow or go with
with shifts that can't met that would
happen so I was I I felt like we had
achieved what they had wanted and they
had the capacity to generate their own
internal capacity because of that
experience and you know in other parts
of my life I would continue to write and
talk about the integral moment and the
integral worldview one of the things I
became aware of was there's just so much
capacity for building capacity in the
integral movement could be coaching
could be facilitation your own work
around regeneration and countering Shawn
Espeon Hargens and you know looking at
integral ecology or Mark decay around
integral sustainable design I just
thought wow these this is really so
interesting that we are able now to be
offer our services in ways that we could
accelerate change in the world
theoretically but we tend to be spread
out all over the place not just in
different cities but all over the world
and so my fantasy has been what would
happen if we brought the leaders of all
these integral specialties together and
imagined that we were in one city and of
course in this period of time the whole
challenge around climate change and
other volatile uncertain complex and
ambiguous aspects of our VUCA world have
arisen of all the wicked problems and so
more than ever I've entertained this
fantasy and I've tried inviting others
at at conferences to convene that kind
of conversation and there's always been
resistance I can't give you an answer
why but it's been very frustrating to me
because on the one hand I've been trying
to take integral perspectives to a world
that doesn't know anything about that
way of looking at the world and then
when I come into the integral movement
there seems not to be an awareness
in particular around the city as a scale
as a scale of human systems because one
thing I've noticed is integral tends to
specialize at the individual development
or leadership or the organization's and
then it'll go to nations and the globe
and I keep saying but there's actually a
scale in between organizations and
nations you can say it like there's just
one question that I don't want to not
ask which is how do you see the
relationship between the city and the
region because for me what I've learned
by being at the lower scale aspect
spending time at finding on working with
transition towns looking at the kind of
almost intentional experiment types of
can we create a sustainable regenerative
system that really heals people and
place I I kind of got to see that that
small community scale is too small to
have the systemic integration to create
the win-win-win with the environment
so really em the by a regional scale the
watershed scale within which for me the
city sits and is is to my mind where we
can redesign the human presence on earth
but of course because now so many of us
live in cities for me the relationship
of energizing by original development
and contextualizing urban city
development in that way is one of the
key challenges for the next decade and i
would love to hear your take on on
region yeah actually I see them
completely as you just described and
it's probably um something like a Susan
Tom do for me
I you know develop these ideas living in
British Columbia which is part of the
Cascadia watershed and I was totally
influenced in the 70s and 80s and 90s by
the discourse that was going on around
that whole set of watersheds
and influenced by the First Nations ways
of actually dividing up their
territories which was by watershed so
it's actually implied in my work and
explicitly written in the book that
looks that you have to engage with with
the ecoregions and more than ever now I
feel that is the only way we're going to
be able to bring coherence to the city
is if there is a deep reconnection with
the ecoregion I was just speaking at the
eco city world summit in didn't
Vancouver with them with Bill Rees who
was you know the co-author of the the
eco footprint and that also I was there
at the very first workshop they ever
gave and so that impressed me deeply and
I have never thought of cities outside
the context of the ecoregions so
reminder Bill breeze was Martin much is
what a bacchanalian s supervisor yes
yeah and then the other person went
there was you know Richard register who
was there the person who originally you
know coined the term eco city so I feel
that they're absolutely inextricably
linked I don't actually separate the
city from the region have you have you
in your own because what I was I mean
this is this is very sometimes my
academic background shows a bit that I
actually love going up swimmingly in the
history of all of this because there's
sometimes so much wisdom to to discover
and and for me um one of the the real
founding fathers of this impulse that I
see both of us still working in is is
Patrick Geddes
um and then Patrick Geddes is linked to
young Christian smokes and and holism
and and how Geddes is this interesting
person who is a biologist who is at the
same time accredited for being the
founding father of town planning
also very at the core of this the
founding of the discipline of sociology
and so he envisioned the the Edinburgh
Festival and he brought people like the
play and inhaler the the guy who coined
the term ecology together in Edinburgh
to bring this synthesis of knowledge
this map making of the the wider picture
and then wrote this wonderful book that
very few people read because it's like
three volumes and it's called life
towards a general biology and which he
co-authored with with a professor at
Aberdeen University and for me he had
this vision that that we're still trying
to bring into the world the world has
taken up a lot more since then but it
was 120 years ahead of his time
yeah I agree totally and I do see us as
as his children I was introduced to
Patrick Geddes by a city planner who I
met in Canada who's Scottish she was now
in fact and is a fanatically devoted
Patrick Geddes and so once I came and
yeah walked up and down the Royal Mile
and appreciated all of Olive Geddes I
had to actually go up to the top of the
camera obscura
and see what he saw there and absolutely
I feel I feel like yin that you just
mentioned that in white also so we've
been in in he and he's been inside the
Academy Academy in Canada and because I
was always an associate at akka division
out of Royal Roads University Ian could
feed me all kinds of things that he just
couldn't you know push too hard in the
Academy and I would go off and
experiment with them I know that you
knew each other but it makes perfect
sense yeah we're very close friends very
close friends so yeah I go visit just
because you mentioned the outlet power
lately through my I was in March I was
in Brazil launching my book in in
Portuguese there and I met some people
who an both with the Museum of the
future in in Rio de Janeiro and then
towards the end of the last year I was
in Barcelona where a small foundation is
also thinking about starting a museum of
tomorrow and somehow I've connected over
the last two or three years to more and
more people who are really living into
this question what is the role of
cultural institutions and museums in the
the necessary public education and
transformative process of basically
creating platforms to have the kind of
conversations you were just explaining
with the work you were doing in was it
an Oklahoman he said hey get Geddes
again was a visionary there with the
outlook tower to basically make
everybody in Edinburgh understand the
scale linking that the fractal dimension
of he is the world he is Europe
he is England here Scotland he is your
city and now you're at the top and not
have a look at your city with really
high technology at the time the camera
yeah yeah but it in one exhibition
people walked up that tower and had a
nested sense of place yeah
given to them in a in an easily
communicated way that educated people
could go deeper less educated people
could just enjoy the experience and and
and and still be very deeply affected by
it
and and I think we that's that's a big
challenge for the future as well too
under that part of kind of a Keynesian
seed of how do we create culture because
I also think that the Edinburgh Festival
was that intention like this he he was
trying to invite us back into synthesis
yeah it's continued another hundred
years
yes began in two hours silos and and
with all the
the negative side-effects that that that
had and of course it if there's a lot of
interesting knowledge but can you bring
it back together again and actually so
that that's really um sparks me because
a number of interests are are
discovering Patrick Geddes totally we
know without city planning background
and saying yes there's there's been in
the Journal of integral theory and
practice an article written on Patrick
Geddes an early integrate integralists
and your description of the outlook
tower sort of is a way for me to say
well that's what I would like to do is
bring all the interests together and say
what if we were in Edinburgh and um
we're now faced with all of these wicked
problems and particularly climate
challenges how would we work together so
that we could offer the ways that the
many new insights that we have around
building capacity how would we do that
so my invitation for this urban hub book
is kind of like that it turns out I
actually also made the same proposal to
the integral Europe conference I hadn't
put the two together until I started to
send the invitations for the urban hub
and I realized how these are actually
just part of a trajectory that I'm
trying to synthesize all this expertise
in in service to cities and ecoregions
so when I finished writing that first
book which was had all of those
intelligence is the last chapter was on
evolutionary intelligence and that
chapter I realized that what I was
really saying in the whole rest of the
book was there was a code there's a
master code that we can live by in
service to human systems and and all
that is and I call it to care for
yourself you must care for yourself so
you can care for others
and we care for others so we can care
for our places and together we can care
for the planet
so like individual others some planet
and that together is is the master code
and I even borrowed from Aurobindo I
think it's like an integral yoga at the
end of every day I asked myself how have
I done that how have I done that caring
for self others placing planet I think
it's interesting because it for me it's
it's a it's a reframing interesting
reframing because if you put your put in
place and then in that way because for
like I understood that the question of
how do I serve self community and life
or planet is is really at the heart of
almost all indigenous cultures like that
is a master quote that is how we as
human beings have learned to live over
millennia in in a sense of a way but but
by putting place in particularly at this
point in time it's it's it's an
invitation to reconnection to the earth
which of course you could say it's in
the how do I serve planet or how do I
serve life but right now what we in so
need is that deeper reconnection and so
I was I just saw that and in general I
think your integral city side is an
incredible piece of work the layers and
layers of mapping you've done and the
synthesizing is um is really like what I
always ask myself is I hope like I
really hope that resources like that
actually get to use that well because
they offer so much but there's so much
out there then I'm often wondering do
people actually find the site and use it
so is that a question
yeah well it's it's a question and it's
but it's also a question for me and it
leads to another question I would like
to to ask you and which is this sense of
urgency of unraveling of
more and more voices falling into acid
apocalyptic tone about the future and
where of course we need to be realistic
about to an extent we've committed
already because of lag in the system of
climate change and so on we've committed
to things getting worse and there
already have been getting worse so much
faster in the last three four five years
which is why people are finally starting
to wake up but but in in this context of
this urgency on this nice edge of of
we're within one limited frame within
just one type of scientific analysis you
could say it's too late possibly but
since we know that there are many
multiple friends and the system is much
more complex and surprising than we
could ever map um how do you how do you
because you and I like we've just talked
about wonderful important needs for
integration but how few people really
care about that at this point in time
how many people are still out there
caring about other things and and how
how does that connect to how much time
we've got left how do we become most
effective in what we do well great
question and one I wrestle with all the
time these days so some of the
inspirations you've already brought
forward I will say one place that I
always believed was important was Gettys
think local act global no think global
act local
but people have reversed it that way and
you know our mutual friend Judy Ravana's
said think cosmic feel global act local
and I feel it's very important for
people to have a local relationship with
earth with place because
that's where their energy will be I
haven't stopped following the energy so
I feel that people care deeply for those
people that matter to them and the earth
I think we see that rising and of course
the media doesn't always play it out as
is what's actually happening locally
like say with extinction rebellion with
it with the local people who have sort
of built on all that years of work out
of transition towns and other other ways
where they younger people have woken up
and said we don't we don't accept this
way of disrespecting the earth which is
what they're pointing to basically
corporations and capitalism as it
currently exists how are we going to
find our way out of here I think we all
have to do it together and I have always
thought that was one of values and
benefits of cities is because in the
developed world ninety percent of us
live in cities when we average it out
across the whole world 60 percent of us
live in cities and I think that that is
where change is happening because it
must cities are where we reflect our
relationships and agreements on a day to
day basis but we also know as the one
thing that globalization has enabled as
most people have some idea that their
food doesn't just come from the grocery
store but they must actually understand
something about ecoregions and/or how
far that food has been transported to
land on their plate so I feel that it's
opening up the same kinds of
conversations I've talked about before
that allows people to be honest in what
they do know and don't know and their
fears because unless you can allow the
pain and the fear and the trauma in the
room then I think that it's very
difficult to go forward I
see some really interesting people doing
major work here
Thomas Huebel would be one of them
Monica Sharma is another you ask me does
my website ever you know do people go to
Allah they must because I have to say
that 2019 was a year where I was not
pushing my itinerary people invited me
to come to parts of the world I had
never expected to go to one of them was
India I just received an invitation to
go to Korea I died I didn't seek either
of those and it was because people have
found my work through either my books or
the website or they found a blog and so
there's something out there that I think
I would even bring into our conversation
the spiritual reality of people seeking
answers not just in a gross realm but
looking to other realms and I think
those answers and that kind of synthesis
is also starting to emerge it's hard
hard to be here infant Horn where we're
celebrating co-founder Dorothy McClane's
100th birthday and look at how her very
simple commitment to living through love
in a very practical way has impacted
people around the world I'm a radical
optimist
in my darkest hours that's what I remind
myself and I come out and it keeps
surfacing I'm afraid I was just made
that way and I I do believe we will see
a lot of change in the near and however
you want to measure the distance in the
future and I think we would I think we
have the capacity to adapt it
of the other I think influences for both
of us has been um James Lovelock I heard
him being interviewed live in Canada
about ten years ago and he said after
they interviewer had described how
terrible humans have treated the earth
that he mustn't have a very high opinion
of humans and he said on the contrary
she cut it right off on the contrary he
says humans are Gaia's reflective organs
I was so astonished I almost drove off
the road I had to change all my slides
because that's where I was going with to
conference and it made me wake up to a
whole other level of respect
responsibility commitment Wow I've been
evolved I've been evolved to be geysers
of the organ I think actually cities are
the organs and we're the cells and
that's a pretty high high calling this
this is so much I think of the changes
that the crisis is pushing in us now
which is really like you've heard me say
this a friend on when I gave this talk
last year and that to some extent we've
pushed life into like out of a
relatively ten-year 10,000 years stable
period where life had a pretty way of
sort of stabilizing planetary conditions
and we've pushed it into an extreme of
ecosystems collapse and possible runaway
climate change and all of those things
in in in that some something is
reminding us that we are life that we
are not from it that we are completely
connected and dependent on it and we're
starting to it like I mean that's when
energy like I want you to panic comes
from bread that true because I don't
think panic is the right energy to find
a solution but that initial kind of it's
getting at us is is a rite of passage is
a pushing us
to face my mortality as a species and as
life to a point where we were ready to
to evolve and grow up and and and part
of it is like it and this is where I
also find it a city so interesting is
that in retelling our story rather than
through the story of separation but
through the story of that fractal nested
into being of that understanding that we
are actually the universe becoming
conscious to itself carry in us the the
molecules forged in supernovas and that
the ring I've got on my finger made from
gold needs the death of a star in order
to create the molecules that make this
possible but every cell in your body has
elements in there that have been part of
this huge story for eons and I always
remembered Johnna Macy
reminding me that if you if you step on
stage and you and you do your work
remember you are speaking on behalf of
3.8 billion years of life's evolution
life is speaking through you you have
the right to say what you need to say
because you're saying it for the larger
being that really the similar ways you
just describe really recontextualized it
makes us more audacious and more humble
see in time and in and I I feel like
we're definitely called to trust that if
consciousness is primary rather than
matter that if we because this is a I
think we're like we've now left it so
far but there isn't a purely rational
reductionist scientific way of getting
out of this dead end that we're pushing
towards unless we zoom out and
understand that even that lens as useful
as it isn't as important as we should
still use science very centrally we need
to go beyond the limitations of our
current scientific paradigm and
understand that
if consciousness is primary then the the
way out of the current dead end
is actually to bring forth the world
differently and that means change our
way of being rather primarily and that
will change the doing rather than
constantly trying to adjust our doing
without questioning the way we are yes
so that's what I feel like part of that
with the city we envisioning the city as
an expression of life and seeing that
anybody who still tells you that
evolution and life is about competition
and scarcity like look you're telling me
that competition has shaped the
evolution of life and then you're living
in a city where if you if you like take
a city like New York with either 15
these days the amount of murders and
violent interaction compared to the fact
that that meant people function as a
super organism that the roads work the
energy comes with all the shortcomings
around the edges is a miracle it's a
miracle of showing us when life is
actually about collaboration and
symbiosis and rather than competition
absolutely absolutely yeah and one or
the other
I think mutual friends that helped me to
affirm that was elisabet sahtouris so
when we met each other 12 years ago or
so you know she was talking about the
cell as a city and I was talking about
the city as a cell and we realized Oh
fractals different scales and just had
so much resonance
how she was seeing the city just as I
was in traveling from 30,000 feet oh wow
this is this is what I call a meshwork
it's actually we can see the built form
and in fact cities are the only human
system you can actually see from space
you can't see the nation's but the
cities you can see you can see where the
energy has been amplified and it's so
important for us to do just what you
have described here to bring that
consciousness in to complement the
biology and the systems that we created
and I've said for a long time my opinion
was that new governance is not going to
come from Nations new governance will
come from cities because we must create
new governance in order to continue to
be able to collaborate together and
that's what Elizabeth says where we are
going through a species maturation
process and that this false story about
the competition as being the only way
forward it has to give way to
cooperation and collaboration and she
can point it the species all around the
earth where this has happened again and
again and again so we are repeating a
natural cycle and our capacity for the
consciousness and the culture to become
aware of our worldview to become aware
that we are consciousness conscious of
itself it is a miracle it's a miracle
but for me one thing that that brings me
back to the one of the deepest insights
I got out of working with the integra
map and what spiral dynamics I know
almost 20 years ago when I first really
got into it and this insight that it is
an evolutionary dynamic map of course
the big problem I always find with the
integral communities that they they lose
themselves in the frameworks of the
theory and get rigid around that but
that's a different story
the developmental part of it like people
who are in the second tier conversations
very often fall into this trap of just
trying to let's if let's lift everybody
up into having this conversation and and
not acknowledging that if this is an
evolutionary process we need to have
space for all the stages in it which
means it will be rednecks in the future
too but but how do you how do you become
a healthy place grounded earth loving
life supporting redneck and and and like
that's again that's bad language or bad
metaphor because I don't my perspective
of rednecks in the slightest but but how
do we create human systems where we see
diversity like we're now learning the
hard way that we deeply depend on on the
on biodiversity and the diversity of
life and that the species extinction
will bring our extinction if we don't
watch out and since we're a complex
species we've gone very quickly the
microbes are gonna and the mushrooms are
gonna come back and bring back life long
after us but but the the how do we
really work with all of our diversity of
opinions and world views and
perspectives in a constructive way that
doesn't try to get into agreement
because never get there but honest
disagreement and diversity in a way as
the source of creativity and
adaptability and vitality then will
allow us to keep evolving into the
future but that shift at this point
where they're such polarization seems to
be so hard to make it's easy to think of
it intellectually but but it's it's yeah
so you just raised something else that
we agree on that was one of the things
that um I really appreciated from Claire
Graves who was the researcher behind
spiral dynamics who said you must allow
people to be who they
at the stage that they are and he was
the first person that I know who really
um managed to see human systems
development within the context of life
conditions so that meant both the
cultural and social and also the
environmental life conditions in my
opinion it wasn't always unpacked that
way but I always saw it that way and a
lot of in integralists don't they forget
about the life conditions piece that
we're co-creating like conditions as
they're co-creating us and that as you
point out as why there is a chapter in
the first book I just published the
second edition of that kept that in
there about generations um you know
people will evolve through their own
lives through these different stages and
I think that one of the ways that we
might shift from polarities is to go
back and reclaim at a new level of
complexity some of the practices from
tribes who had life passages through
these different stages and celebrated
them so that there was healthy read as
you say it's gonna happen so they had
ways of bringing young people into their
manhood or womanhood and they had rites
of passage where they learned both the
energies of that value system and that
capacity and that made them ready for
when they would move on into a more
complex system and the thing that cities
offer us is very cook the large cities
you mentioned the year well I was in in
Delhi in India 26 million people and I
was really curious what I would see
there so I I was looking for a lot of
diversity I was quite surprised at how
modern the city is because I had all
kinds of ideas and stereotypes and in my
mind but also looking at the different
layers of the ways that people lived in
their habitats on the streets with the
different transportation systems how I
would say globalization has really
impacted and destroyed a lot of
flow in the culture and sped it up to
such levels of risk and threat that it's
truly for somebody who doesn't live
there on a regular basis
very causing me to live on the edge of
my seat you've been there you know that
I once took a took took from cannot
circus to the Sun Abaza area of Delhi
and it was probably like my adrenaline
levels whenever I know I know but but
within cities whether it's New York or
Delhi that the cities where there is so
many cultures mixing we're having to
find diversity not in just how we make
decisions or the whole but how those
decisions are made for the smaller parts
of the whole where we still have groups
of people who want to stay together
because that's their choice but in the
city they have to figure out how are we
going to live here well this very
different group of people lives here and
I think cities will continue to be a
place where if we don't get integration
will will get all kinds of synthesis
that some of which we can't even imagine
now some some some will be I will create
whole new convergences because people
will decide they they will come together
but I think we'll see quite much more of
what I would call an ecology of cultures
that will find it like a forest has a
million niches and I think that a city
even if we just looked at say a modern
city it has that that's what makes it
work is the capacity to share labor and
find niches that allow us to grow I
think we're going to find that will
intensify intensify even more and so if
we I would agree and I'm just thinking
how do you impose the enabling
constraints of living within a planets I
have physical boundaries yeah systems
that you also want to be as diverse in
their expression and and cultural
exploration as possible in with within
that is also the question of do we just
accept that technology has been created
in such a way so far that it has almost
become an autopoietic runaway system
that that we're now running after rather
than guiding or do we understand that
since all technology is ultimately human
intention turned into some form of
design process like machinery and so on
that we also have potential of choosing
not to use technology because that's
like there's a bifurcation nevermind if
the physical danger of life unraveling
there's also a technological danger of
us bifurcating into a different type of
technologically enhanced species that
that might create some opportunities but
will also kill a lot of what
evolutionary life has been about so far
you know I think that's one thing that
cities as a whole are tend to still be
very disconnected with and that is there
I believe they have a responsibility to
their bio region so and this is I think
in most cities everywhere there's no
awareness that they have a
responsibility to know where their
energy literally their their their
foodstuffs energy and life stuffs energy
is coming from and how to replenish it
so one of the other things we haven't
mentioned is that I call cities human
hives and I have learned from the
biomimicry study of bees particularly
honeybees that they actually have a
double sustainability loop so they have
organized the hive so that they produce
their twenty kilograms of honey a year
and that's where the four voices come
from the four voices that I use in the
city I have learned from the bees
and in order to do that though they
pollinate the ecoregion and as they
pollinate they are actually creating
energy for next year so the pollination
process serves them for the energy now
but also the energy in the future and
the pollination serves all of the rest
of the ecology that their hide exists in
and that I think is the set of
principles that I think the cities need
to learn
I think yetis knew that I think that was
one of the he also loved feeds and I
think he pointed to the same kinds of
relationship could you just briefly
repeat the four voices because you
mentioned him a number of times and just
also for its other people listen to
bring them back into people's awareness
yep so the four voices in the city are
the citizens and in the Beehive those
are the forager producers in the city
the second voice is the civic manager so
that's like everybody City Hall
Education Health Public Works emergency
fire police and in the Beehive we would
call those resource allocators the third
voice are I call them business
innovators but innovators of all kind
and in the Beehive they're called
diversity generators they're actually
intentionally there to bring in
innovation and and source new sources of
energy and then the fourth voice in the
city is the third sector or a civil
society and in the Beehive I think
that's actually the inner judges or the
hive mind and that and that the hive
mind
and the resource allocators in the
beehive are the ones that tell us tell
the hive are we on track to produce our
twenty kilograms of honey but in so
doing they also are enabling that um
double loop of of sustainability to go
on so those are the four voices in the
city citizens and civic managers
business innovators and civil society
initially you know that there's this
whole movement around the 4th sector
networks and which work with the kind of
traditional business sector public
sector in NGO sector and then they
called the fourth sector the the people
who who like in a nutshell definition
use the tools of the business world to
address the problems that the private
sector the public sector isn't
addressing effectively but with the
ethics of the third sector the NGOs and
civil society and have you ever come
across people confusing those four
voices and the four sectors no I haven't
yet because I haven't been in a
discourse like that but I would say
that's very interesting because I am
noticing that often times two or three
of those voices are turning up sometimes
four and slightly different variations
on them because people have you know
they maybe develop them from a rational
analysis as I said I was inspired
through a biomimicry to say oh I think
this is this pattern that the bees have
actually exists at the city we just
don't see it we don't use that pattern
but I started to call it I started to
call the voices together around the same
table and I noticed the difference and
the difference prevented the
polarization because the bees are
serving the health of the individual as
well as the health of the whole um the
city needs to do both that and the
health of the eco of the health of the
planet that's why that layers of the
master code really matter and I see how
I it's it's so interesting
of course you'd expect that but learning
and deepening into the kind of
regenerative practice work that that is
curated and held by-by the Regenesis
Institute by Ben Haggard and Pamela
Mannion and Bill Reid and and all these
wonderful people I've I've
recognize so many of my own frameworks
that have together and integrated and
synthesized over the last 20 years and
and fell the real parallel evolution and
the similarly as I listen to you and and
and as I was navigating the entire city
website I realized wow like this we
could talk for weeks still have lots of
points of deepening because it is a
fractal thing we could dive off in every
direction but this has been in
incredibly rich and before we finish and
you briefly mentioned this this urban
hub series and you yet invited me to
contribute some something to it in in
the next edition and can you tell a
little bit more about that project
because we already are on the 12th
edition awesome something like that oh
well yes well this urban hub series is
actually now they've produced the 19th
one we're going to get the 20 will be
urban hub 20 which i think is a
beautiful nice symmetry 20 I'm looking
for 20 contributors in 2020 for urban
hub 20 so this series was created by
Paul van Schaik so Paul van Schaik is
his organization integral Mentors
he's been working as one of the earliest
integral practitioners his first
organization I think is called I shake
and and I remembered seeing it on Ken
Wilbur's website and discussions with
him very early on Paul is also the
co-founder of integral Without Borders
so he works with Gayle ha-cha-cha
and looking at how to bring integral and
often into places in the developing
world but Paul is also an architect and
so he decided that his writing would be
mostly graphic or at least 50% graphic
in focus and he created a series of
graphic books and he's published them so
that they're all free and downloadable
on the issue web site and you can also
get a hard copy to run off of Amazon but
I've contributed to four or five of them
and he
brought different themes together and
different practitioners from around the
world and the basic layout of the book
is very makes it very appealing I write
you know very long narratives in my
books but Paul looks that 50% of the
message be graphic and 50% be narrative
and so how we invite contributors is
could you give us 6 PowerPoint slides
because that's actually how we produce
the book and 50% of your slides it can
be each slide or how every wish however
you wish to allocate it bring bring your
message in a way that will be
graphically appealing for readers and
not just the meaning that you're making
in the words so when Paul I shared Paul
with Paul my fantasy about bringing all
the integralists together for one city I
like I said what if that happened we
could we could take a topic like climate
change and how would we all surpass and
he looked at me and said well why don't
you curate an urban hub to do that so I
took that on and when I started to think
about it
the first major frame to curate around
was the master code I thought well I
will invite people who are thinking
about planet people thinking about place
people thinking about capacity
development and others and thinking
about capacity development in
individuals and asked them what if you
were all together in one city
what would you contribute to building
capacity so we could mean climate
challenge I chose climate as sort of the
example so you're one of the people I
invited to contribute at the planetary
scale and I think in our discussions you
also obviously have a great heart for
place and you obviously are well
practiced and seeing the fractal
patterns so I would love it if you could
just
from this conversation some of the
comments that you were making about the
importance of city to relate to
ecoregion to relate to watersheds and
show how that contributes on a planetary
scale you might want to borrow from
Geddes I would be very happy for for
that to turn up in the book I have
contributors from all of the other
scales in the master code so I think
it's going to be I think we're going to
have our our 24 20 20 and I had another
piece of synchronicity happen I've been
appointed to be a fellow of the urban
arena who are looking at sustainability
and justice over the next two years we
visiting about 400 different research
projects and seeing if we can bring them
together and offer them forward to
European cities and while I was sharing
the urban hub project with a woman from
Lisbon it turned out they have a really
nice integral group of thinkers in is
Lisbon and they volunteered their city
to be on target city for like okay what
you bring in for the urban hub will look
at and see how we could do that and
enlist them because I think that if we
do this in the one you know it'll be in
the urban hub 20 that it'll become like
a prototype at the intera Europe
conference we're going to have the you
theory as one of them and that's one of
the final things that you do is the you
Theory autogyros work is you come up
with a prototype so in effect I think
will produce a prototype that could be
used at any city or village even because
I imagine we can use this thinking back
and pinpoint even and Lisbon is willing
to take it on as urtica a first trial
and see what they can learn from what we
could call together what's the timeline
he said contributions end of general
yeah that one my invitation went out in
December I was targeting the end of
January yes I'm open to a little bit of
negotiation if you need and the book is
it because in that way you could
probably produce it relatively quickly
is it because this year 2020 Lisbon a
city of yes it is yes as a mother
synchronicity
yes I didn't know that when when they
came forward yes the brew the book will
be produced by April I will be taking it
to the integral Europe conference in May
so yes this is one of the wonderful
things Paul having done 19 of them has a
very strong idea of just exactly how to
do the production and because they're
first produced as ebooks then then
they're also all downloadable by
everybody and that also makes it
wonderfully accessible so much better
well I'm looking forward to writing a
piece if you feel free to critique the
first one like because you have a more
editorial understanding of something
that you expected me to put in missing
when you get the piece let me know and
see what we can do okay well that's a
wonderful invitation back to me because
I'm also remaining quite open and this
will be an example of living with
diversity in the city because I won't
know exactly how it should all be
curated until I see everybody's
contributions so I'm learning I have my
first one already on mindset which was
really nice contributions come in very
quickly and yeah so I will get back to
you if I having questions and I just
anticipate a lot of energy because
that's what I feel for me thank you so
much for this time and a part of me
could easily continue for another hour
but I think him we will do another time
have a wonderful beginning to the year
and and yeah enjoy those quiet times at
fintan and I always find this is a
special time
before the Year really gets going it's
maybe another week or so where he can
like I certainly allow myself most
exploration of sort of the passions and
the creative impulses that that are
wanting to be brought into the year that
that I might miss out on if I don't give
them attention now yeah it's I love this
time of year so wonderful so much for
our conversation thank you okay thank
you I know in the recording